third of September Monday Palma de
Majorca Spain planet Earth this is my
first attempt at trying to create some
kind of video diary it probably be
sporadic and no on a regular basis but I
thought I'd share how the visit of
Professor Anthony Capone then went he is
the world's first professor for
planetary health based at the University
of Sydney and he's also a co-author of a
recent report that was created by The
Lancet Commission and the Rockefeller
Foundation on planetary health and what
it means to safeguard planetary health
in the Anthropocene so while I'm not so
keen on the the wording of the
Anthropocene but that's a whole nother
story was real surprised to me in a way
about four five weeks ago he contacted
me told me that he was in Europe and
that between a conference in Bali with
future Earth in a number of meetings in
London and in Cambridge he had some time
and he wondered whether it would fit my
schedule for him to come down to Majorca
so we could have a conversation and I
was really quite surprised and flattered
that he would take that time out to come
and see me and what transpired in our
conversations that while he's been
working with this group of
ecological epidemiology technologists
and mainly medics with some system
scientists on developing this concept of
planetary health he found himself to be
one of the most realistic and widely
thinking people in that group and when
he did some research on the evolution of
the planet planetary health concept he
came across some of the papers that I
wrote while I was doing my PhD research
between 2004 and 2006 and some papers
that I wrote in 2006 just after I
published my PhD my PhD was on design
for human and Planetary health a
holistic integral approach to complexity
and sustainability and because it was in
a design school I could break a number
of established boundaries for PhD work
because at the time PhDs and design was
still relatively new and I had come in
on a scholarship from like the
scholarships by the faculty I was at the
Jordan School of Art and Design the
Center for the study of natural design
which is run by my mentor and my PhD
supervisor professor Stephen Baxter who
I owe a tremendous debt of gratitude to
and basically
in that work I sketched out what it
might mean to design for human and
Planetary health and I used my
background in complexity theory in Earth
System science what I learned at
Schumacher College in the master's in
holistic science to advance a theory of
how health is really an emergent
property in complex dynamic systems and
it emerges through the interactions and
relationships of all the agents in that
system and emerges at different scales
that are interconnected so I use this
idea of scale linking how the local is
ring linked to the regional to the
bioregional to the local ecosystem and
the global and how health really depends
on
right relationships and healthy dynamics
that it allowed the health of the whole
to express itself because ultimately the
whole has a healthy dynamic as it
evolves but of course everybody who
participates like each one of us and the
whole of humanity influence the health
of the whole and so yeah this notion
that individual health community health
bio regional ecosystems health and
Planetary health are intimately linked
and that ultimately health is the
pattern that connects and is a scaling
pattern has strongly influenced Anthony
Capone's thinking and through him also
to some extent that new Commission on
planetary health and so for me that's a
real exciting used to find out I was
aware of the report but to be contacted
by one of its principles and to be told
that this PhD research that I did more
than 10 years ago actually had made a
difference to them is giving me an
enormous gratification and joy and and
also I feel like all that hard work has
not been in vain and maybe I was just a
little bit ahead of my time because at
the time when I tried to get
postdoctoral research funding I had a
brief postdoctoral fellowship from the
University of Dundee and I just couldn't
get any funding being in a design school
when I wrote to the Arts and Humanities
Research Council they said this is
terribly scientific it's all about
ecosystems restoration and about
renewable energy and sustainable
transport sustainable cities sustainable
product design but from a very
scientific perspective dealing with
climate change and and
well at the time it they weren't called
planetary boundaries but basically
dealing with the planetary boundaries
and and so they said why don't you talk
to the art said the environmental and
physical science Research Council they
might fund something like that and so
when I did that they would then come
back to me and say but you're in a
design school what are you talking to us
for and when I wrote to both of them
copying him into the replies that I'd
gotten from me they basically said why
don't you go and talk to the Social
Science Research Council because you
don't fit here or maybe even the
Economic Research Council might be
willing to take this on long story short
I back then just couldn't get any
funding in conventional macademia they
were talking about interdisciplinarity
and transdisciplinarity but they were
just not ready for it and these big
questions were just something that
nobody wanted to fund so in a way that
was a kind invitation to doing what I've
done in the 12 years since which is to
dance on the edge between more
pioneering educational NGOs and projects
that are practically on the ground
experimenting with how we might create a
more sustainable and thriving future and
occasionally link them into work with
universities and with local and national
government and so
to find now that there's actually
momentum that there's now a professor
for planetary health in it that already
Harvard has now created another chair
that also has the word planetary health
and the title it's something like
environmental restoration and planetary
health and Anthony came on Thursday
picked him up from the airport we had a
nice conversation in the afternoon and I
walked by therefore by the sea and then
we spent the whole of Friday really
talking in a very wide-ranging wonderful
conversation about how we might
collaborate and how he sees that field
evolving and then I also saw him again
on Saturday evening for just a final
check before he left on on Sunday and
initially we intended to record part of
our conversation on Saturday but in the
end it was such a nice evening and we
were sitting watching the sunset and
just got talking and decided that we
could always do the recording on his own
call and so watch that space so we
talked about a huge range of topics but
what we both agreed on is that even
within this budding movement of
planetary health there's still a need
for a much more holistic approach and he
said what he liked about my work is that
it focused on change it focused on how
can we actually make an influence and
become planetary healers how can we work
on restoration and regeneration and he
even brought a copy of my book asking me
to sign it and and complimented me on on
that work and
basically he said that not everybody in
that community is aware of my work but
he would like to help them find out
about it because it has this very
holistic approach and then he showed me
a graphic that shows how he now in his
talks Peale who conceives and introduces
planetary health and it is very much
linked to what I was calling scale
linking issues in my PhD how do we move
people how do we house people how do we
feed people how do we provide energy for
people and how do we fit into this world
how do we heal the health dynamics at
ecosystems and planetary levels and so
in talking about the sea also absolutely
agreed on the necessity for a
bioregional approach that that while we
definitely need to work local in all
localities everywhere and that saluto
genic health generating regenerative
design has to be carefully adapted to
the bio cultural uniqueness of place is
abroad with that he also agrees that
these local initiatives have to be fully
aware of the nested holds they sit in
and the next wider hole the bio region
is critically important his own work is
in mainly in city health and of course
cities sit within a particular bio
region
so you could say local community cities
by a region if you if you want to be
more granular in this scale inking
approach but then we also agreed that to
some extent the the national scale isn't
really something that has a sort of
biological precedence it's it's a
completely socially constructed concept
to say this is where the line you can
see it when you look at the maps like so
many particularly in in the former
colonies so many borders have been
drawn by the people in power with a
ruler and their straight lines and
that's not how the biomes and the
ecosystems that they these straight
lines cross actually function so we we
both agreed that as we're talking
seventh generation thinking in deep
transformations of the human presence on
earth what we should hold in mind is
that national boundaries are an
anachronism that we might well find that
won't be part of the future in which
humanity has learned to act as a
planetary healer and appropriate
participant in the emergence of health
at all scales within the planetary
system and I thought that was also very
encouraging that that we agreed on this
and of course it's a very politically
tricky issue because very difficult to
talk to state actors to international
leaders and basically say you unit of
administration and governance might be
an anachronism in the planetary era but
maybe it is also important to open this
conversation because so much of national
boundaries have been created in a time
but relatively recently at the end of
the era of empires as Robert Gilman puts
it five thousand year period where we
started to create systems of power over
and power against rather than power with
and it's the split of our unity and
enter being with the natural world that
created environmental scarcities that
then created the need to fission in the
device divide and conquer the human
family
and so we created these artificial
boundaries through religion and also
through national boundaries so one of
the things another thing that we talked
about is how ecosystems regeneration is
vitally a restoration is vitally
important and how hopeful it is that
unit and a number of actors are now very
strongly behind the idea of creating a
decade for ecosystems restoration which
would start in 2020 and run until 2030
and really that is our last hope that in
that decade there is such a push towards
regeneration everywhere restore
ecosystems restoration on all levels
that we really see a shift into what
I've been calling the century of
regeneration the the time where we
really turn back the clock on the
massive damage that humanity has caused
on planet Earth and begin to reverse
that damage and show that as life we are
capable of creating conditions conducive
to life and we also talked about how we
need to raise awareness that this scale
linking characteristic of health is
going on at all scales that basically
you can start with cellular health it is
about what kind of enzymes what kind of
nutrients cellular nutrients and and how
much water everything like the dynamics
within a single cell which is in itself
already a complex dynamic system
dynamics that can either lead to the
emergence of health as a
property of that complex dynamic system
of ill-health and then since that cell
in many cases sits either in an
environment or in a wider multicellular
organism organelles is a agglomeration
of cells and their emergent health so
the health of cells affects the health
of organs our heart our brain our lungs
our vital functions and of course that
affects the complex dynamic system which
is a human individual and the emergence
of health at that scale and then we need
to be aware that and we look at the
scale of the human being and emergence
of health at that scale we need to
understand that we are walking
ecosystems we are actually on us and in
us there are more non-human cells than
there are human cells we carry microbial
fungal bacterial cells in our guts on
our tongue in our mouth cavity on our
skin everywhere around our eyes all of
that contributes to maintaining a
healthy human body so we are walking
ecosystems and the health of the
ecosystems within